hi everyone welcome back to this is
science
i'm dr matt fedorick chief science
officer at usada
today we're here to talk about the
difference between junk science
and real science you hear junk science
on the internet
on social media at the dining room table
at your parents house talking with your
friends
we want to set the record straight and
today we're here to talk
specifically about vaccines
all right we're here to talk about
vaccine myths
and today we're going to talk about four
common vaccine myths that you may have
heard
myth number one is the development of
vaccines was rushed
it's true that these vaccines came to
market
in record time but before they came to
market they went through
very detailed safety and efficacy trials
in thousands of humans to test both
their safety
and if they worked their efficacy they
were tested across
ethnicities age groups as well as
across different geographical locations
around the countries
looking for the side effects as well as
how well they worked
to prevent infections of the covid virus
okay myth number two is that the pfizer
and moderna mrna vaccines
change your dna i'm gonna show you why
that's not true
okay so this is a piece of mrna
it's packaged inside a fat molecule
or a lipid this is how it gets into our
cells
this technology has actually been around
for decades
and it's been developed for other flu
vaccines as well
like influenza and zika although covid
is the first time it's been put into
production
here once you have the medicine made it
gets injected into our bodies
it goes to our cells and that mrna
is the instruction book that instructs
our cells
to make a small piece of the spike
protein
that is actually the same spike protein
that's on the outside
of the virus once that protein is made
that gives our bodies the signal to make
antibodies those antibodies are part of
our immune system
once those antibodies are made if we're
infected
with the virus that antibody
recognizes that piece of protein that
spike protein
on the outside of the cell and allows
our bodies to more
effectively recognize and fight that
virus more quickly
than without the antibodies the dna down
here in the nucleus
you can see the mrna never interacts
with the dna
so in that way dna cannot be changed by
the vaccine okay myth number three
is that the vaccines don't protect
against variants
this has actually been looked at by
scientists
the various variants that are out
circulating around the world
it seems like the current vaccines are
effective
still against these variants but the
concern that scientists have
is that the longer these variants and
the virus circulate
around the globe the current vaccines
may not be effective
therefore we may in the future need
things like
booster shots in order to continue to
protect against
future variants that may appear and
finally myth number four
is that if you've had covid you don't
need to be vaccinated
we know that people that have been
infected with covid
can get re-infected after a period of
time
but the with the vaccine the efficacy
rate
against preventing infection is upwards
of 95
or 96 now you have the facts
around that some of the top covid19
vaccine myths
go to reliable resources such as the cdc
for the latest information
on vaccines and how to protect yourself
your friends and your family
we know there's a lot of opinions out
there but
this is the real science